Guide to the Thomas Cripps Film Collection, 1898-1976 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Cripps Film collection 1898-1976 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cripps, Thomas
5.5 linear feet Extent: About 975 Items
Retired professor of history at Morgan State University, scholar of the history of African Americans in the motion picture industry, prolific author of books and articles on the subject, and script writer. The Thomas Cripps Film Collection dates from approximately 1898 to 1976, and is arranged into two divisions: films, and official studio publicity photographic stills of African American actors and productions. The thirty-seven reels of film, which have been transferred to VHS viewing copies, are mainly film shorts, clips from feature films, newsreels, "Soundies," and television commercials, and were collected by Thomas Cripps for their portrayals of African Americans, performance by African Americans, or production by African Americans from the turn of the century into the late 1960s and 1970s. He also collected materials reflecting other racial and ethnic stereotypes. The photographic prints, of which there are several hundred, consist of publicity stills and other images taken from U.S. and British feature films with African American actors from the silent film era through the 1970s. One significant group contains stills from the movies of pioneer African American director Oscar Micheaux (1884-1951).
crippsthomas
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Thomas Cripps Film Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Biographical Note
Thomas Cripps is a retired professor of Morgan State University, an historian specializing in the portrayal of African Americans in film, and a published author. Cripps has written five books, including Slow Fade to Black: The Negro in American Film, 1900-1942 (Oxford, 1997), as well as many articles and television scripts. In addition, he has contributed to the production of several television series such as American Cinema, Hollywoodism: Jews, Movies and the American Dream, and Richard Wright: Black Boy. Cripps was awarded gold medals in international film festivals for his 1976 script, Black Shadows on a Silver Screen. In this collection of films and still photographs, Thomas Cripps documents African Americans and their cultural respresentations in the 20th century, and the developing cinematic industry in the U.S. and abroad.
Collection Overview
The Thomas Cripps Film Collection dates from approximately 1898 to 1976, and is arranged into two divisions: films, and photographic stills from films.
The thirty-seven films, which have been transferred to VHS viewing copies, are film shorts, clips from feature films, newsreels, "Soundies," and television commercials, and were collected by Thomas Cripps for their portrayals of African Americans, performance by African Americans, or production by African Americans from the turn of the century into the late 1960s 1970s. He also collected materials reflecting other racial and ethnic stereotypes. The films can be used to study a variety of themes and subjects: African American artists; political and social events; educational institutions for African Americans; the Depression; television culture and advertising; and racial or ethnic stereotypes (chiefly African American, but also Jewish, Irish, and Asian). Many of the early films feature cityscapes of New York, Baltimore, and San Francisco, and other urban scenes, some from as early as 1898 and 1900. Some portray African Americans in several wars, including the Spanish-American War, World War II, and the Korean War. Other films document civil rights era events. Recorded political events include a Harry Truman speech concerning the Civil Rights Commission report, and a Lyndon Johnson speech on civil rights. Among the many notable actors and performers in the films are Duke Ellington, Jesse Owen, Louis Armstrong, Lincoln Perry ("Stepin Fetchit"), and Bert Williams. The entry for "Paisan - the Black Story" refers to Rossellini's film on the relations between Italians and American GIs during World War II, "Paisan," in which one episode centers on an African American GI and a Neapolitan street urchin.
Entries for original film reels include the approximate length of the film and other information when possible; titles are retained as found on Cripps' original labels or notes. Viewing copies for these films are available on VHS. Note: Viewing copy titles provide a more accurate account of content and running time.
The photographic prints, of which there are several hundred, consist of publicity stills and other images taken from U.S. and British feature films featuring African American actors from the silent film era through the 1970s. Many entries, which have been retained from the original envelope labels, carry titles from individual films, but other prints were arranged by Cripps into topical categories such as "Black Athletes," "Jungle Pix," "Silent Films," and "Exotic Primitives." One significant group contains images from the movies of pioneer African American director Oscar Micheaux (1884-1951). Arranged as received, in alphabetical order by film title or topical heading.
Acquired as part of the Duke University Archive of Documentary Arts.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Cripps, Thomas; African American artists; African American soldiers; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans in advertising; African Americans in mass media; African Americans in motion pictures; African Americans in the motion picture industry; African Americans -- Pictorial works; Baltimore (Md.)--Pictorial works; Civil rights movements -- United States; Documentary films -- United States; Micheaux, Oscar, 1884-1951; Minorities in motion pictures; Motion picture journalism -- United States; Motion pictures -- United States -- History; Newsreels -- United States; New York (N.Y.)--Pictorial works; United States -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Race in motion pictures; Race relations -- United States -- 20th century; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.)--Pictorial works; Silent films -- United States; Motion pictures; Silent films; Black and white photographs; VHS (TM).
Contents of Collection
- Films Series, circa 1898-1968, (40 reels or rolls)
  Original films donated by collector Thomas Cripps. Films are primarily primarily black and white, silent, and 16mm. In some cases, rolls of film were found in one canister. Arranged as received.
  [Original recordings are closed to use. Viewing copies are available for all films.]
  - Reel 1, 16 mm positive print, (100') (Box 1)
    North Star on Morgan State University News; Man walking down street
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 1
  - Reel 2, 16 mm positive print, (75') (Box 1)
    March on Washington crowds, 1963
  - Reel 3, 16 mm positive print, (50') (Box 1)
    Black cavalry marching home from Spanish-American War
  - Reel 4, 16 mm positive print, (25') (Box 1)
    Madison Square, NYC, 1898
  - Reel 5, 16 mm negative, (150') (Box 1)
    Truman on Civil Rights Commission report and News in Brief (negative)
  - Reel 6, 16 mm positive print, (150') (Box 1)
    Los Angeles Riots, 1968; Selma March
  - Reel 7, 16 mm positive print, (600') (Box 1)
    Footage of various historically black colleges (Morgan Footage)
  - Reel 8, 16 mm positive print, (450') (Box 1)
    Baltimore fire of l904; vote against Daylight Savings; volunteer information for WWII
  - Reel 9, 16 mm positive print, (100') (Box 1)
    World War II footage with African American soldiers; Newsreel footage ­"Mrs. Roosevelt helps dedicate Negro Boys Club"; "Robot Cotton Picker"
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 2
  - Reel 10, 16 mm positive print, (300') (Box 1)
    Street scenes ­1900s; black soldiers disembarking, Spanish-American War; Eisenhower/Kennedy/LBJ plead for race equality
  - Reel 11, 16 mm positive print, (350') (Box 1)
    Duke Ellington and his Symphony in Black
  - Reel 12, 16 mm positive print, (500') (Box 2)
    Uncle Tom's Cabin (Edison)
  - Reel 13, 16 mm positive print, (600') (Box 2)
    St. Louis Blues
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 3
  - Reel 14, 16 mm positive print, (550') (Box 2)
    Jesse Owens Footage; Signal Corps; Unidentified speaker with several takes; Living conditions ­ Great Depression, l930s
  - Reel 15, 16 mm positive print, (150') (Box 2)
    Students at Booker T. Washington Institute; WWII: Tuskegee Airmen
  - Reel 16, 16 mm positive print, (600') (Box 2)
    Various Scenes from New York City: Military Procession; Arrival of Immigrants, Ellis Island; Panorama from the Times Building, NYC: Sorting Refuse at an incinerating plant, NYC; Union Iron Works; Harlem Street Scenes; Elevated Railroad, NYC; Bargain day, 14th St.; Dick Croker leaving Tammany Hall; Cardinal Gibbons.
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 4
  - Reel 17, 16 mm positive print, (800') (Box 2)
    Ethnic Films:The Black Hand (Biograph); Romance of a Jewess (Or A Jewish Tragedy) (Biograph); The Heathen Chinese and the Sunday School Teacher (Biograph); Cohen's Fire Sale; Alfonse and Gaston Helping an Irishman
  - Reel 18, 16 mm positive print, (800') (Box 2)
    His Trust and His Trust Fulfilled
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 5
  - Reel 19, 16 mm positive print, (900') (Box 2)
    "Soundies": Ellington, Fats Waller, Wingy Manone, Jimmy Rushing, Count Basie, Satchmo
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 5, 6
  - Reel 20, 16 mm positive print, (1200') (Box 2)
    Sunday on the River
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 6
  - Reel 21, 16 mm positive print, (700') (Box 3)
    Mr. Blabbermouth
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 7
  - Reel 22, 16 mm positive print, (50') (Box 3)
    Misc. Seventies TV commercials
  - Reel 23, 16 mm positive print, (1300') (Reel 23)
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 7, 8
  - Reel 24, 16 mm positive print, (1400') (Reel 24)
    The Negro Soldier
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 8, 9
  - Reel 25, 16 mm positive print, (1700') (Reel 25)
    Black Shadows on a Silver Screen
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 9, 10
  - Reel 26, 8mm, (length unknown) (Box 3)
    A Natural Born Gambler
  - Reel 27, 16 mm positive print, (350') (Box 3)
    Spying the Spy (l9l9) - silent
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 10
  - Reel 28, 16 mm positive print, (50') (Box 3)
    Thurgood Marshall joining the Supreme Court (newsreel); Selma - Montgomery March (Universal Newsreel); LBJ speech
  - Reel 29, 16 mm positive print, (200') (Box 3)
    Sidney Poiter accepts Oscar; Negro Youth Administration footage, l930s
  - Reel 30, 16 mm positive print, (150') (Box 3)
    LBJ greets troops; News in Brief ­ Social Security; Black troops, Korean War
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 10, 11
  - Reel 31, 16 mm positive print, (300') (Box 3)
    City Scenes: New York City scenes, circa l900; Star theater; NY skyscrapers from North River; 1st Avenue - Seattle, Washington; San Francisco from balloon; Battery Park, NY; Cotton spinning
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 11
  - Reel 32, 16 mm positive print, (400') (Box 3)
    Paisan - The Black Story
  - Reel 33, 16 mm positive print, (200') (Box 3)
    Watermelon Contest, Gator and the Picka-ninnie, A Bucket of Cream Ale, silent
  - Reel 34, 16 mm positive print, (350') (Box 3)
    Open the Door, Richard, with Lincoln Perry ("Stepin Fetchit")
  - Reel 35, 16 mm positive print, (250') (Box 3)
    Panorama, Union Square, San Francisco; Cardinal Gibbons; Cake Walk; Cavalry Troops; NY Street Scene; Gesture Fight on Hester Street (Part 1)
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copies 11,12
  - Reel 36, 16 mm positive print, (150') (Box 3)
    Panorama, Union Square, San Francisco; Cardinal Gibbons; Cake Walk; Cavalry Troops; NY Street Scene; Gesture Fight on Hester Street (Part 2)
  - Reel 37, 16 mm positive print, (300') (Box 3)
    The Fights of Nations, silent
    Use Copies: VHS use copy available. See viewing copy 12
  - Reel 38, 16 mm positive print, (350') (Box 3)
    Rhapsody in Black and Blue with Louis Armstrong (Satchmo), directed by Aubrey Scotto
  - Reel 39, 16 mm positive print, (500') (Box 3)
    Buck Dance, Broken Doll, silent
  - Reel 40, 16 mm positive print, (300') (Box 3)
    (unfinished) Spying the Spy,
- Still Photographs Series, 1902-1976, (3 boxes)
  Consists of hundreds of black and white publicity stills and other images collected by Thomas Cripps over many years, taken from films featuring African American actors or African American producers and directors from the silent film era through the 1970s. Almost all derive from American-made films, but there is also a large group of stills originating from British films. One significant group contains images from pioneer African American director Oscar Micheaux's movies. Titles refer either to individual films, or to broad subjects. To improve housing, contents of original envelopes have been refoldered, but Cripps' content lists which provide fuller descriptive access to individual images have been photocopied and placed in each folder with its corresponding group of stills. A few folders include other film publicity or correspondence. Arranged as received, in alphabetical order by film title or topical heading. Original folder titles were retained. Dates added by archivist are in brackets.
  - Bojangles As Butler, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - Jim Comes to Jo'burg, 1949
  - Island in the Sun, 1957
  - Jungle Pix, 1930
  - Joanna, 1968, (2 folders)
  - The Joe Louis Story, 1953
  - Jungle Drums of America (12-episode serial), 1953
  - Key Largo, 1947
  - Lilies of the Field, 1963
  - Lydia Bailey, 1952
  - Mark of the Hawk, 1957
  - Message Movies, 1949-1952
    - Bright Victory (or Lights Out), 1951
    - Stars In My Crown, 1950
    - Home of the Brave, 1949
    - The Intruder [1962]
    - Lost Boundaries, 1949
    - Detective Story, 1951
    - Intruder [1962]
    - Five, 1951
  - Moan and Groan [1929]
  - Maps, Cartouches, 1971-1976 and undated
  - Moonrise, circa 1948
  - Muse, Misc., 1933 and undated
  - Network, 1976
  - Nothing But A Man, 1960
  - Odds Against Tomorrow, 1959
  - Our Daily Bread, 1933
  - Oxford, Volumes 1a-1c, 1 (foreign), undated, (9 folders)
  - Panther Girl of the Kongo, 1955
  - The Pawnbroker, 1965
  - A Raisin in the Sun, 1960
  - Race Pix (Reinkens Films), undated
    Includes two negative slides and letter to Thomas Cripps from Sharon Reinkens.
  - St. Louis Blues, 1957
  - The Set Up, 1949
  - Shaft, 1971-1972
  - Simba, undated
  - Song of the South, 1944
  - Sounder, 1972
  - Stormy Weather, 1943
  - Topsy and Eva, 1928
  - Trader Horn, 1929
  - To Live In Peace [1947; TV version, 1951]
  - Take a Giant Step, 1959
  - Uncle Tom's Cabin, 1903 (Box 2)
  - Watermelon Man, 1970
  - The Well, 1951
  - The World, The Flesh, and The Devil, 1958, (2 folders)
  - Young Man with a Horn, 1950
  - The Young One (Great Britain title: Island of Shame), 1960
  - Eddie "Rochester" Anderson, 1940-1945
  - Black Athletes, 1940s-1960s and undated
    - Jack Johnson, undated
    - The Joe Louis Story [1953]
    - Easy Living, 1949
    - The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, 1960
    - This is the Army, 1943
    - Kenny Washington, undated
    - None But The Brave, 1965
    - The Fiercest Heart, 1961
    - Satchel Paige on Rutledge Set
  - Black Performers As Selves, 1930-1965
  - Blackface Cycle, Post-Sound, 1930
  - Blackface Roles and Routines, 1920s-1950s and undated
  - Blaxploitation Pix, 1960s-1970s, (2 folders)
  - Pre and Blaxploitation Misc., undated
  - Blaxploitation Misc. TV, undated
  - Jim Brown, 1960s-1970s, undated
  - British Overseas Productions, 1930s-1960s and undated, (2 folders)
    - Orfeo Negro, 1959
    - Tamango, 1959
    - Flame in the Streets, 1961
    - Pennywhistles Blues [1952]
    - Cairo, 1960s
    - Sapphire, 1959
    - Sea Wyf [Sea Wife, 1957?]
    - Dingaka, 1965
    - Stanley Baker, undated
    - Woman of Straw [1964]
    - Men of Two Worlds [1946]
    - Calvert and Adams, undated
    - Guns at Batasi [1964]
    - Young and Willing [1943?]
    - Voice of the Hurricane [1964?]
    - Sanders, 1935
    - Simba, 1955
    - Zulu [1964]
    - The Outcast of the Islands [1952]
    - Rhodes of Africa, 1938
    - Jew Suss, 1935
    - Tiger Bay, 1934
    - Proud Valley, 1940
    - Timbucktoo, 1937
    - Men of Two Worlds, 1946
    - Guns at Batasi [1964]
  - Integrationism, mid-1960s
  - Kung Fu Movies, 1973
  - Mantan Moreland, 1940s
  - Oscar Micheaux Films, 1920s-1930s, (2 folders)
    Includes promotional brochure and negative images of brochure.
    - Wages of Sin [1929]
    - Temptation, 1928
    - Chorus Line, Temptation, 1928
    - Underworld [1937]
    - When Men Betray, 1925
    - Black King, 1931-1932
    - Unknown Title with Charlie Moore and Ethel Moses, 1929
    - Easy Street, 1931
    - Daughter of the Congo, 1927
    - Unknown Title with Pearl McCormick and Rex Ingram, 1920s
    - Millionaire, 1928
    - The Notorious Elinor Lee [1940]
    - Harlem After Midnight [1934]
  - 1940s Conventional Themes and Roles, (2 folders)
    - Vanishing Virginian [1942]
    - Four Jacks and a Jill, 1941
    - Belle Starr, 1940
    - Ziegfeld Follies, 1944-1946
    - Margie, 1947
    - Duel in the Sun, 1946
    - Texas, 1940
    - Johnny Come Lately, 1947
    - Panama Hattie, 1942
    - Free For All, 1949
    - Dakota, 1946
    - My Brother Talks to Horses, 1947
    - The Music Goes Round [1936?]
    - Three Stooges, 1940s
    - Heaven Can Wait, 1943
    - Major and the Minor, 1942
    - They Won't Belive Me, 1947
    - Duffy's Tavern, 1945
    - Monsieur Beaucaire, 1946
    - Gas House Kids, circa 1950
    - Born to Kill, 1946
    - High Barbaree, 1947
    - Senator Was Indiscreet, 1947
    - Cairo, 1940s
    - Secret of Dr. Kildare [1939]
    - Ghost Breakers, 1940
    - Gorgeous Hussy [1936]
  - 1945-1949 Pre-Message Movie Intimations
  - Of Orientals, 1917-1961 and undated, (2 folders)
  - Vietnam Newsshots [1960s-1970s?]
  - 1960s Pre-Blaxploitation Pix, (2 folders)
  - Poitier, Sidney, 1954-1971
  - Production Crew Shots, 1929-1973 and undated, (2 folders)
  - Sammy Davis Jr., 1950s-1960s
  - 1930s Deviant Pix
  - European Ethnic and Immigrant Groups, 1920s-1960s
    - Moulin Rouge, undated
    - Abes's Irish Rose, 1946
    - Jazz Singer, undated
    - The Golem, 1921
    - America, America [1963]
    - The Last Hurrah [1958]
    - Humoresque, 1947
    - Sherlock Holmes and Nazis?, 1941
    - Man They Could Not Hang [1939]
    - Ride The Pink Horse, 1947
    - Ride Vaquero, 1953
    - Sweet Rosie O'Grady [1926 or 1943?]
    - Straedy Company (or Cobble Stones), 1932
    - Potash and Perlmutter, 1923
  - Exotic Primitives, 1929-1968, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Indians, 1930s-1950s
  - Silent Pix, 1911-1925 and undated
    Appears to be one still per film. Many but not all are captioned on the back.
    - A Colored Girl's Love, 1915
    - Daughter of Mine, Goldwyn [1919]
    - Peter Pan [1924?]
    - Smith Baby's Birthday [also known as Baby's Birthday, 1929]
    - Lady Rose's Daughter, 1920
    - Little Old NY, 1923
    - Black Wife (?), 192-
    - Smith's Rodeo, undated
    - Senor Jim [1936]
    - What's Your Husband Doing? [1920]
    - Kentucky Colonel [1920]
    - Kentucky Derby [1922?]
    - The Blind Goddess [1948]
    - Day of Faith [1923]
    - Al's Troubles [1926]
    - His Trust, 1911
    - The Perfect Clown [1925]
    - Seven Chances, 1925
    - Fable of the Galumptious Girl [1915]
    - Swim Princess [1928]
  - Token Integrationism, 1950s, (2 folders)
  - Trainers and Racetracks, 1945 and undated
  - Van Peebles, undated
  - Publicity One-Shots, undated, (13 folders)
    - Movies A-M, (4 folders)
    - Movies N-Z, (2 folders)
    - Performing, (5 folders)
    - Unknown, (2 folders)
  - Unidentified Films, undated, (4 folders)
  - Oversize Material
    - While Thousands Cheer, 1940 [removed from the Blaxploitation miscellaneous folder] (Oversize-box 20)